## **Max Chen**

Known Alias: Jingru Chen Email: mjchen@wpi.edu Website: https://users.wpi.edu/~mjchen

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am a PhD student in Interactive Media and Game Development at Worcester Polytechnic Institute, where I am a member of Crafting Computational Crafting Lab, <u>Intentional Design Studio</u>, and <u>HCI Lab</u>. My research focuses on computational design, with a particular emphasis on developing novel interfaces for immersive environments such as video games, virtual reality, and augmented reality. Particularly, I am interested in exploring design strategies that leverage biofeedback and neurofeedback to enhance user experiences in video games. As a research assistant at WPI Academic & Research Computing, I develop, implement, and evaluate digital media products that support and promote faculty research, teaching, scholarship, and external partnerships.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD in Interactive Media & Game Development

Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI), Worcester, MA Advisors: Prof. Gillian Smith and Prof. Erin Solovey

#### Master of Science in Interactive Media & Game Development

Worcester Polytechnic Institute (WPI), Worcester, MA Advisors: Prof. Gillian Smith and Prof. Erin Solovey

#### **Bachelor of Engineering in Pharmaceutical Engineering**

Wuhan University of Technology, Wuhan, China

Aug 2016 – June 2020

Aug 2022 - Present

Aug 2020 - Dec 2022

#### RELEVANT SKILLS AND COURSEWORK

**Programming**: C#, Python, MATLAB, Java, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, C++

Software and Tools: Unity3D, Unreal Engine, GitHub, Plastic, Adobe Creative Suite, Qualtrics, Turbo Satori (NIRx)

**Courses**: Tangible and Embodied Interaction, Brain-Computer Interaction, Design of Interactive Experiences, Multidisciplinary Research Methods in Computational Media, System Dynamics, Learning Sciences

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **JOURNAL ARTICLE**

Max Chen, Yichen Li, Hilson Shrestha, Noëlle Rakotondravony, Lane Harrison, Robert E. Dempski, FlowAR: An
effective mixed reality program to introduce continuous flow concepts. [Manuscript under review]

#### **CONFERENCE PAPERS**

 Max Chen, Yihong Xu, Alexander Sirois, Yichen Li, Robert Dempski, Gillian Smith, Yuko Oda, Yunus Telliel, Erika Lewis, Kelilah Wolkowicz, WheelUp! Developing an Interactive Electric-power Wheelchair Virtual Training Environment. IEEE Conference on Games (CoG '23). Boston, USA, August 2023 [Accepted]

- Max Chen, Erin Solovey, Gillian Smith. Impact of BCI-Informed Visual Effect Adaptation in a Walking Simulator.
   Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games (FDG '23). Lisbon,
   Portugal, April 2023
- Max Chen and Shamsnaz Virani Bhada. Converting Natural Language Policy Article into MBSE Model. INCOSE International Symposium. Vol. 32. 2022.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

- Robert Dempski, Claire Li, Max Chen, Shano Liang. Integrating Biophysics Immersive Learning Tools Across
   Campus. Building a Network of Biophysics Education, Virtual, June 2022
- Robert Dempski, Andrew Texeira, Claire Li, Shano Liang, Max Chen. Integrating Immersive Learning Tools across Campus and Beyond. Advanced Manufacturing and Processing Conference, Washington DC, June 2022
- Max Chen. The Importation of Murder Mystery Games in China Game Localization and Creativity. Canadian Game Studies Association Annual Conference, June 2022

#### **INVITED TALK**

IEEE VR 2023 Workshop on VR for Exergaming (VR4Exergame)

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **Research Intern,** The Roux Institute at Northeastern University, Portland, ME

June 2023 - Present

I conduct research in using biometric sensors for evaluating emotional responses.

# **Research Assistant,** WPI Academic & Research Computing, Worcester, MA I provide AR/VR training & technical expertise to students and faculties, prototype AR/VR and other educational technologies for various needs. I write and maintain intuitive and accessible documentation on equipment (HoloLens 2, Quest 2, Matterport), and maintain internal websites for demonstrating showcases.

Feb 2021 - Present

**Senior Member,** WPI Intentional Design Studio, Worcester, MA I develop VR/AR apps, from design to maintenance phase, working on teams of 3-6 programmers, designers, and artists. Our collaborators and clients are from WPI, Delsys Technology, UMass Lowell, Doherty Memorial High School, etc.

Sep 2020 - Present

### **AWARDS & GRANTS**

- 2023 Graduate Student Travel Award
- 2023 Foundations of Digital Games Travel Assistance Program (TAP)
- 2023 Supporting WPI Women in STEM Education Research
- 2022 Third Place in WPI 14th Annual Sustainability Project Competition
- 2022 Mentor, Women in Research and Mentorship Program

#### **PROJECTS**

Stack AR Sep 2022 - Present

This project investigated the design affordances of transparent film paper and how it can be used in augmented reality (AR). We apply participatory design framework in creating AR-based learning tools with educators, students and learning scientists.

#### WheelUp: Co-design a VR Wheelchair Simulator

Sep 2022 - Present

This project builds the bridge between developers and user community. We developed a VR wheelchair simulator to train users in driving electric wheelchair using various input mechanics in a safe environment.

Flow Chemistry AR Sep 2020 – March 2023

This project involves the development of a HoloLens AR application to instruct on packed bed column assembly and assess its effectiveness in a flow chemistry laboratory session.

#### **BCI-informed Game Visuals (MS Thesis)**

Oct 2021 - Dec 2022

This project aims to explore the use of brain-computer interface (BCI)-adapted visual effects to support atmosphere in a walking simulator game and investigated its impact on player-reported immersive experience. I developed an open-sourced interface from functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) acquisition and processing tool to Unity3D.

### **VOLUNTEER/SERVICES**

- Graduate Student Representative for IMGD Program Committee (2023)
- Graduate Student Union Member (2022)
- Workshop Mentor at Latino Education Institute, Worcester State University (November 2022)

#### TEACHING/MENTORING EXPERIENCE

#### **Undergraduate Major Qualifying Project**

Amanda Jones, Megan Letendre, Elise Nerden. "Sewn into Memory: Reliving Feelings through an AR Quilt"
 (2023)

#### Women's Research and Mentorship Program

- Rachel Foye, Ava Stockton, and Dinah Agyemang. "Food Chain AR: Co-design an Augmented Reality Book with Educators and Students" (2022)

#### **Guest Lectures**

- WPI IMGD 3100: Novel Interfaces for Interactive Environment, "Brain-computer Interfaces and Games" (2023)
- Massachusetts College of Art and Design Artward Bound Program, "Implementing Augmented Reality to Emphasize the Impact of Climate Change" (2022)
- Girls Talk Math, "Number Systems" (2023)